MUHAMMAD ABDUL JABBAR

Jakarta,Indonesia | +6282119101825 | abdul.jabbar.3794@gmail.com | linkedin.com | Github.com/thejabbar

PROFILE SUMMARY

Al/ML Engineer with a proven track record of successfully implementing industry-standard solutions in Generative Al, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and Natural Language Processing. Strong engineering background with extensive experience in the finance and telecommunications sectors.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

- Bahasa Indonesia Native
- English Business/Professional Level
 - o IELTS: 7.0
 - TOEFL ITP 607
- Japanese Daily Conversation Short Course

TECHNICAL EXPERIENCE

- Python 9 Years
- SQL 7 Years
- Data Science 7 Years
- Machine Learning/Deep Learning 7
 Years
- Natural Language Processing 7 Years
- Generative AI / AI Engineering 3
 Years
- Git, CI/CD, Docker, DevOps 3 Years

EDUCATION

Master of Business Data Science

2017 - 2018

University of Otago

Study focus: Advanced Analytics Methodology and Use Cases in New Zealand Business Environment Research Thesis: Computer Science Research Trend Identification using Latent Dirichlet Allocation and K-means Clustering

Bachelor of Computational Science

2011 - 2015

Telkom University

Study focus: Financial Computing, Machine Learning, Data Mining, Artificial Intelligence, Swarm Intelligence.

Research Project: Analysis of Academic Student Admission of Telkom University using Ant-Miner Classification Algorithm.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Artificial Intelligence Engineer

February, 2023 - Present

Telkom Indonesia

- Developing custom Al solutions and capabilities for internal use cases such as Generative Al chatbots, computer vision, and Machine Learning model, e.g HR Demography Al Chatbots, Account Manager Sales Assistant Chatbot, Visitor Surveillance Facial Recognition Engine and Dashboard, OCR and VLM Document Checker Chatbot, etc
- Researching current trends in AI e.g RAG and Advanced RAG, Agentic Chatbots, MCP, , Gen-AI
 OCR, etc.
- Developing, testing and maintaining scalable deployment of open source Large Language Model (LLM) and Large Multimodal Model (LMM).
- Deployment, monitoring, and maintenance of AI service APIs in Cloud based environment such as Kubernetes system. and Azure Environment.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Junior Analyst Data Scientist Bank Indonesia

February, 2019 - February, 2023

- Developing end-to-end macro-economy, monetary, macro-prudential, payment system and market policy advanced analytics use cases using machine learning and data science, e.g news sourced policy credibility measurements. time series bond market forecasting, payment system trend dashboards, etc.
- Managing multiple projects deadline and collaboration with other department and divisions
- Developing and maintaining statistics and data infrastructure.
- Responsible in routine and ad-hoc big data provision for policy formulation.

Artificial Intelligence Researcher

December, 2019 - February, 2019

Smart City Community and Innovation Center, Bandung institute of Technology

- Developing social media sentiment analysis for the city of Bandung
- Research in customer service Bahasa Indonesia intent prediction speech-to-text model.

Data Scientist Codigo

June, 2018 - October, 2018

- Developing Natural Language Processing (NLP) in Bahasa Indonesia models for Aksara.Al platform such as sentiment analysis, Named Entity Recognition (NER), and Text Summarization models using Long Short Term Memory (LSTM) deep learning model and Text Mining.
- Developing Hoax Classifier using Long Short Term Memory (LSTM) Deep Learning model.
- Natural Language Understanding (NLU) Chatbot research.
- Delivering product features on time according to deadline and collaborate with DevOps, Project Management, and Product Divisions.

PUBLICATIONS

IFC Conference on Post-pandemic Landscape for Central Bank Statistics

August, 2022

Irving Fisher Committee on Central Bank Statistics, Bank of International Settlements

- Measuring Macroprudential Policy Credibility Using Machine Learning
- Measuring Payment System Policy Credibility Using Machine Learning

IFC Workshop on Data Science in Central Banking: Applications and tools

February, 2021

Irving Fisher Committee on Central Bank Statistics, Bank of International Settlements

- Sentiment Analysis of Tourist Reviews from Online Travel Forum for Improving Indonesia Tourism Sector
- Machine Learning for Measuring Central Bank Policy Credibility and Communication from News
- Big Data Analytics on Payment System for Measuring Household Consumption Indicator in Indonesia

IFC Workshop on "Data Science in Central Banking"

October, 2021

Irving Fisher Committee on Central Bank Statistics, Bank of International Settlements

 Predicting Foreign Investors' Behavior and Flows Projection in Indonesia Government Bonds Market using Machine Learning

WORKSHOP AND COURSES CERTIFICATION

Google Advanced Data Analytics Specialization Google

September, 2024

• Advanced data analytics methodology certification in GCP Environment

Microsoft Certified: Azure Al Engineer Associate

July, 2024

Microsoft

• Fundamental certifications of Al Application in Microsoft Azure environment.